{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Responses to these documents were penned by Robert Yates, George Clinton, and Mercy Otis Warren. The fifty-first of these documents praises \"the greatest of all reflections of human nature\" in a description of \"checks and balances.\" For 10 points, name these documents which were written by John Jay, James Madison and Alexander Hamilton in favor of the Constitution.",
      "answer": "Federalist Papers"
    },
    {
      "question": "The third generation of this group was bankrupted in 1981 by a lawsuit engineered by Morris Dees. This group originally formed in Pulaski, Tennessee and was targeted by the Force Act, but formed again after a 1915 meeting on Stone Mountain. Nathan Bedford Forrest was the original Grand Wizard of this group, which targeted Republicans and black voters. For ten points, name this white supremacist organization, which dressed in white hoods.",
      "answer": [
        "Ku Klu Klan",
        "KKK",
        "the Klan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This person's name was formerly used for the capital of Tajikistan, now known as Dushanbe (doo-SHAHN-bay), and for the mountain now called Ismail Samani (suh-MAH-nee) Peak, which was called \"Communism Peak\" after his death. For 10 points, identify this former namesake of Volgograd, where a major World War II battle was fought in the Soviet Union.",
      "answer": "Joseph Stalin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This modern-day country was converted by Saint Frumentius in the 4th century. The rock-cut city of Lalibela is in this country, where inscriptions in the Ge'ez language appear on stone stelae in the ancient city of Axum. The coffee plant was first grown in this modern-day country. For 10 points, name this African country which lost access to the Red Sea when Eritrea seceded.",
      "answer": "Ethiopia"
    },
    {
      "question": "IBM introduced the first consumer model of this device in 1975 under the name \"3800.\" In the 1980s, Apple manufactured a popular line of these devices in the Writer series. These devices were invented by Gary Starkweather, who came up with the idea of using an \"image drum.\" For 10 points, name these high-speed, toner-consuming devices for paper output.",
      "answer": "laser printers"
    },
    {
      "question": "These agreements were condemned by the United Nations in Resolution 33/28 A. As a result of signing these agreements, one negotiator was killed by Khalid Islambouli and Islamic Jihad. These agreements established the border and a peace agreement between Egypt and Israel. For 10 points, name these 1978 agreements negotiated by Jimmy Carter at a Presidential retreat.",
      "answer": "Camp David Accords"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was drafted in the 21st round by the Philadelphia Eagles in 1958, but a knee injury ended his playing career a year later. However, during the 1970's, he led the Oakland Raiders to a 76.3% winning percentage in the 142 regular season games he coached. He later was as a commentator for ABC's Monday Night Football. For 10 points, name this former football player, coach, and commentator who is known for endorsing NFL-based video games bearing his name.",
      "answer": "John Madden"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man, who had a vision of dew falling on grass during a solar eclipse, was interviewed by Thomas Gray after his capture. This man killed the Travis family before his capture at Jerusalem, and he is fictionalized in a William Styron book about his \"confessions.\" For 10 points, name this leader of an 1831 slave rebellion in southeastern Virginia.",
      "answer": "Nat Turner"
    },
    {
      "question": "Many participants in this event came from Mary Ann M'Clintock's Yearly Meeting movement, which sought to reform decision-making among Quakers. Frederick Douglass spoke at this event, which adopted the Declaration of Sentiments. For 10 points, name this 1848 convention at which Lucretia Mott and Elizabeth Cady Stanton began the women's rights movement.",
      "answer": "Seneca Falls Convention"
    },
    {
      "question": "This instrument's Pleyel models were preferred by its greatest twentieth-century player, Wanda Landowska. The \"art\" of playing this instrument was discussed by François Couperin, and Domenico Scarlatti wrote extensively for it. For 10 points, name this instrument for which J.S. Bach frequently composed, which plucks strings instead of striking them like the later piano.",
      "answer": "harpsichord NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Tokyo Two were members of this group arrested for stealing cetacean meat. This organization was funded by an Irving-Stowe-arranged benefit concert at Amchitka. A ship belonging to it was docked at a New Zealand harbor when it was bombed by French agents; that ship was the Rainbow Warrior. For 10 points, name this militant environmentalist group",
        "answer": "Greenpeace"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which other conservation group was founded by John Muir after a namesake mountain range?",
        "answer": "Sierra Club"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Oscar Kokoschka depicted Alma Mahler as this kind of person “of the Wind.” A Rembrandt depiction of this kind of person was thought to be a father giving his daughter a necklace. Another kind of person is shown wearing a green dress and having a dog at her feet. For 10 points, name this type of person who in a Jan van Eyck (Yon van IKE) portrait marries Giovanni Arnolfini.",
        "answer": "Bride"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Dada artist of Fountain painted The Bride Stripped Bare by Her Bachelors, Even?",
        "answer": "Marcel Duchamp"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A founder of one of these parties in Italy argued states maintain power through controlling culture in his Prison Notebooks. Parties by this name were instructed to join Popular Fronts during the 1930s to oppose fascism. This party is still the dominant political party in Laos and Vietnam. For 10 points, name these parties promoting the theories of Karl Marx.",
        "answer": "Communist parties"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Yugoslav leader took his country out of Cominform after a dispute with the Soviet Union over the Greek civil war?",
        "answer": "Josip Broz Tito"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire built the Qhapaq Ñan by pioneering a forced labor system called mit'a. Messengers called chasquis relayed messages along its elaborate road system, which was paved with stone so llamas and alpacas could traverse them. For 10 points, name this South American empire run from Cuzco, which built Machu Picchu.",
        "answer": "Incan Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What as-yet undeciphered strings of knotted, colored cords were used by the Incas to convey messages about quantities of goods?",
        "answer": "quipus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, French forces mutinied en masse following the failure of the Nivelle Offensive. Alexander Samsonov was killed during it when un-coded radio messages helped lead to the defeat of two Russian armies at Tannenberg. Anzac Day celebrates the Australians and New Zealanders who died during this war. For 10 points, name this 1914 to 1918 war.",
        "answer": "World War I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Aside from Austria-Hungary and the Ottoman Empire, which other country in the Southeastern Balkans fought on the side of the Central Powers in World War I?",
        "answer": "Bulgaria"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man and his wife made the first English translation of Agricola's Latin text on mining, De Rerum Metallica. He often conversed with his wife in Mandarin, and was the leader of Belgian food relief efforts after World War I. For 10 points, name this President who defeated Al Smith for election but suffered the start of the Great Depression in his first year in office.",
        "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hoover was born in which Midwestern state, where Barack Obama’s first presidential bid got a boost when he won its caucuses in 2008?",
        "answer": "Iowa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author was to be profiled by C.S. Forester after his career as a fighter pilot ended, but chose to begin his own writing career instead with an autobiographical article. He also wrote the memoir Going Solo, and this man’s Norwegian mother named him after the first man to reach the South Pole. For 10 points, name this author of James and the Giant Peach and Charlie and the Chocolate Factory.",
        "answer": "Roald Dahl"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dahl wrote the screenplays for You Only Live Twice and Chitty Chitty Bang Bang, film adaptations of books by what creator of James Bond?",
        "answer": "Ian Fleming"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An advocate of this philosophy wrote The Great Divorce and the early feminist text Woman in the Nineteenth Century. This philosophy, whose journal The Dial was edited by Margaret Fuller, also included the man who wrote \"that government is best which governs least.\" For 10 points, name this philosophy of mid-nineteenth-century Americans such as Henry David Thoreau.",
        "answer": "transcendentalism"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other transcendentalist delivered the lectures \"The American Scholar\" and \"Nature\" to audiences which were shocked by his apparent atheism?",
        "answer": "Ralph Waldo Emerson NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "ROMAN EMPERORS",
      "prompt": "Which Roman emperor…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was a member of the Second Triumvirate who became the first emperor?",
          "answer": "Augustus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Blamed the Christians for the Great Fire of Rome during his reign?",
          "answer": "Nero"
        },
        {
          "question": "Made his horse a Senator and was assassinated by members of the Praetorian Guard?",
          "answer": "Caligula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Had his victory in the Dacian Wars commemorated with a namesake column in Rome?",
          "answer": "Trajan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Established the Flavian dynasty as the last ruler of the Year of the Four Emperors?",
          "answer": "Vespasian"
        },
        {
          "question": "Appointed three co-emperors, establishing the Tetrarchy?",
          "answer": "Diocletian"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the namesake of a book by English author Robert Graves?",
          "answer": "Claudius"
        },
        {
          "question": "Succeeded Julius Nepos and was deposed by Odoacer, making him the last Western Emperor?",
          "answer": [
            "Romulus Augustulus",
            "Romulus Augustus"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "STATES IN THE CIVIL RIGHTS MOVEMENT",
      "prompt": "During the civil rights era, in what U.S. state did...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ruby Bridges integrate schools in New Orleans?",
          "answer": "Lousiana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jackie Robinson take the field at home for the Brooklyn Dodgers?",
          "answer": "New York"
        },
        {
          "question": "The first sit-in take place in Wilmington?",
          "answer": "North Carolina"
        },
        {
          "question": "James Meredith integrate the state university in Oxford?",
          "answer": "Mississippi"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Watts riots occur?",
          "answer": "California"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bull Connor try to stop integration in Birmingham?",
          "answer": "Alabama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Orval Faubus attempt to block the integration of Central High School?",
          "answer": "Arkansas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Protestors beat a man with an American flag on a pole during an anti-busing riot?",
          "answer": "Massachussetts"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ANDREW JACKSON",
      "prompt": "Name the andrew jackson...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Represented what political party?",
          "answer": "Democrats"
        },
        {
          "question": "Currently appears on what denomination of currency?",
          "answer": "twenty-dollar bill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ordered the removal of Cherokee on what \"trail?\"",
          "answer": "Trail of Tears"
        },
        {
          "question": "Campaigned for what \"dark horse\" to be elected in 1844?",
          "answer": "James Knox Polk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Opposed what kind of institution's national charter?",
          "answer": "national bank"
        },
        {
          "question": "Won the Battle of New Orleans two weeks after what treaty was signed?",
          "answer": "Treaty of Ghent"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was scandalized by the snubbing of a Cabinet member's wife in what \"affair?\"",
          "answer": "Eaton affair"
        },
        {
          "question": "Owned a home that shared its name with what Russian art museum?",
          "answer": "The Hermitage NHBB B 2014-2015"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An anonymous proposal suggested finding this value by having wounded dogs bark at regular intervals. After the Scilly Islands disaster in 1707, a prize was created for the person who could create a (20 pts)",
        "method for finding this value. Some of that prize money was awarded to John Harrison, whose marine (10 pts)",
        "chronometer gave sailors an accurate time that could be used to calculate it. For 10 points, name this geographic coordinate that identifies East- West position, as opposed to latitude."
      ],
      "answer": "longitude"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Saint Telemachus was stoned to death while attempting to stop an event involving these people. These people, who were managed by a lanista, participated in the most famous of the munera. One of these people led a 73 BC (20 pts)",
        "revolt that was put down by Crassus. Types of these people include the murmillones, who had fish-shaped crests on their (10 pts)",
        "helmets, and the retiarii, who used nets. For 10 points, name these Romans, including Spartacus, who engaged in public armed combat for entertainment."
      ],
      "answer": "gladiators"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This modern-day country was the birthplace of an order founded by Stephen Hunting and spread by St. Bernard, the Cistercians. During a massacre of heretics in this country, the order \"kill them (20 pts)",
        "all- God will know his own\" was given. After the death of Peter of Castelnau in this country, Innocent III ordered a campaign against the gnostic (10 pts)",
        "Cathars of this country, the Albigensian crusade. For 10 points, name this country, home to the Cluny Abbey in its Aquitaine region."
      ],
      "answer": "France"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man attempted to use Gamma Draconis to measure the distance to a star using parallax, but was unable to obtain accurate measurements. This man's observations of a cork plant are collected in his (20 pts)",
        "Micrographia. This longtime leader of the Royal Society in the late seventeenth century also proposed a (10 pts)",
        "\"restoring force\" proportional to distance. For 10 points, name this English polymath who lends his name to a law for the action of springs."
      ],
      "answer": "Robert Hooke"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A popular hippie song said to \"wear a flower in your hair\" when travelling to this city. This city suffered the \"White Night (20 pts)",
        "riots\" following the acquittal of a former supervisor who used the \"twinkie defense\" after killing George Moscone and (10 pts)",
        "Harvey Milk. In 1989, this city was hit by an earthquake while hosting a World Series game. For 10 points, name this city where historic districts such as The Mission and Haight-Ashbury are located."
      ],
      "answer": "San Francisco"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This character was created in 1941 for Pep Comics. He is the namesake of a company that published Super Cops and Mighty Crusaders under the Red Circle imprint, and he often irritates the wealthy Mr. (20 pts)",
        "Lodge. In the 1970s, this character was the leader of a fictional band that sang the song (10 pts)",
        "\"Sugar, Sugar.\" For 10 points, name this red-haired comic book character who hangs out in Riverdale with Jughead, Betty and Veronica."
      ],
      "answer": "Archie Andrews"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Protestors in this country in 2014 often wore the number forty-three painted on their faces, a reminder of the September 2014 abduction of forty-three (20 pts)",
        "students at a teachers' college here. Protests targeted this country's president, who represents the (10 pts)",
        "PRI and defeated the incumbent PAN in the 2012 election. For 10 points, name this country where protestors demanded the resignation of Enrique Peña Nieto (en-REE-kay PEN-yah nee-EY-toe)."
      ],
      "answer": "Mexico"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This state’s loss at the first Battle of Himera led to the downfall of its Magonid dynasty. The Fabian strategy was developed to fight the armies of this city, which won battles at (20 pts)",
        "Trebia and Lake Trasimene after one of its commanders crossed the (10 pts)",
        "Alps. Cato the Elder famously ended his speeches by declaring that this city “must be destroyed”, or “delenda est”. For 10 points, name this city-state whose armies, led by Hamilcar and Hannibal Barca, fought Rome in the Punic Wars."
      ],
      "answer": "Carthage NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ]
}